Guide to the Yale School of Drama Doctor of Fine Arts Theses
Yale University Arts Library
Yale School of Drama Doctor of Fine Arts Dissertations
1958-2014
DRA 27
Yale University Arts Library
21.68
(52 boxes)
The collection consists of dissertations written in partial completion of the requirements for the Yale School of Drama Doctor of Fine Arts degree.
Yale School of Drama
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Yale School of Drama.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This is a collection of dissertations written in partial completion of the requirements for the Yale School of Drama Doctor of Fine Arts degree.
Arrangement
Arranged in chronological order by year of completion, then arranged alphabetically by author surname within each year.
Drama -- History and criticism; Dissertations
- Dramaturgy and Dramatic Criticism Doctoral Dissertations
  - Shaw's Shakespearean Criticism, 1958; Wilson, E. E., Jr. (Box 1)
  - The Stage Spectacles of Philip James de Loutherbourg, 1960; Allen, Ralph G. (Box 1)
  - Themes of Tennessee Williams, 1960; Clayton, John Strother, 1925- (Box 2)
  - Form and Content in the Plays of Sean O'Casey, 1960; Ritchie, Harry M. (Box 2)
  - Jean Nicolas Servandon: His Scenography and His Influence, 1960; States, Bert O., 1929- (Box 3)
  - Theme and Attitude in the American Musical Theatre, 1961; Kenvin, Roger (Box 3)
  - The Chorus in Contemporary Drama, 1961; Wenneker, Jerome S. (Box 4)
  - A Critical Analysis of the Plays of Lillian Hellman, 1962; Brockington, John (Box 4)
  - Shakespearean Playwriting Techniques: A Dramaturgic Comparison of Hamlet with Its So-Called Bad Quarto, 1962; Zuckerman, Albert J. (Box 5)
  - Sidney Howard: American Playwright, 1963; Scott, Charles E. (Box 5)
  - The Productions of Chekhov's Plays on The American Professional Stage, 1964; Raviv, Zeev (Box 5)
  - Symphonic Outdoor Drama: a study of form in the plays of Paul Green, 1964; Staroba, Frank J. (Box 6)
  - The Satire of Charles Hoyt, 1964; Swortzell, Nancy Foell (Box 6)
  - The Mozart Operas and the Director, 1965; Balk, H. Wesley (Box 6)
  - Jean Giraudoux: Three Faces of Destiny, 1965; Cohen, Robert S. (Box 7)
  - The Theatricalization of Modern American Drama, 1965; Eysselinck, Walter (Box 7)
  - Edward Albee: Social Critic, 1965; Rutenberg, Michael E. (Box 7)
  - Inter-Influence Between Drama and the Pictorial Arts During the Middle Ages, vol. I, 1965; Sensenbach, Alfred David (Box 8)
  - Comedy and Tennessee Williams, 1965; Starnes, Leland (Box 8)
  - The Negro on Broadway: The Transition Years, 1920-1930, 1965; Woods, Porter (Box 9)
  - The Trinidad Carnival: a study of its form and content as the basis for a national theatre, 1966; Hill, Errol (Box 9)
  - Henry Irving and "Natural" Acting, 1966; Novick, Julius, 1939- (Box 9)
  - Gasconade For the End of the World: The Plays of John Osborne, 1966; Strane, Robert Erskine (Box 10)
  - Tragedy and the Artist, 1967; Epstein, Leslie (Box 10)
  - The Modernity of Thomas Middleton, 1967; Hallett, Charles A. (Box 10)
  - Tennessee Williams and the Southern Myth, 1967; Hashim, James E. (Box 11)
  - The Comedy of Illumination of S.N. Behrman, 1967; Hickenlooper, George (Box 11)
  - The Performance of H.C. Andersen's Plays at the Danish Royal Theatre, 1967; Marker, Frederick J. (Box 12)
  - Arthur Wing Pinero and Victorian Farce: A Critical Study, 1968; Burwell, Richard (Box 12)
  - Theatricality in the Avant-Garde: An Objective Analysis of Selected Plays of Pinter, Beckett, and Ionesco, 1968; Juergens, Robert Oscar (Box 12)
  - The Shaping of King John, 1969; Price, Jonathan R. (Box 13)
  - John Ford: Mirror of an Age, 1969; Bierhaus, E. G., Jr. (Box 13)
  - The Comedie Rosse of Henry Becque and The Critics, 1969; Coy, Stephen C. (Box 14)
  - A History of the San Francisco Actor's Workshop, vol. I, 1969; Fowler, Keith Franklin (Box 15)
  - A History of the San Francisco Actor's Workshop, vol. II, 1969; Fowler, Keith Franklin (Box 16)
  - An Historical and Critical Study of the Serious Plays of Philip Barry (copy 1), 1969; Gild, David C. (Box 14)
  - An Historical and Critical Study of the Serious Plays of Philip Barry (copy 2), 1969; Gild, David C. (Box 17)
  - Stephen Phillips and the Attempt to Revive Verse Drama in England 1899-1915, 1969; Steerman, James B. (Box 17)
  - Intimate Relationships in Tennessee Williams' Plays, 1969; Berkman, Leonard (Box 18)
  - The Bancrofts at the Prince of Wales's: Seven Crucial Seasons (1865-1871), 1970; Kleb, William E. (Box 18)
  - One Revolution: The Shakespeare Memorial Theatre, 1970; Teush, Bart (Box 19)
  - Scribean And Other Influences on Chekhov's Dramaturgy, 1971; Cole, Carroll (Box 19)
  - Peter Brook and the Living Event, 1971; Dawes, Carroll Cecily; 2 (Box 20)
  - Harold Pinter: Plays of Paranoia, 1971; Kranes, David (Box 21)
  - The Early Plays of Sean O'Casey: A Study in Dramatic Experience, 1972; Lyon, Bret (Box 21)
  - Michel De Ghelderode: The Theatricalization of the Playwright's World, 1972; Breslow, Maurice (Box 21)
  - Heroism Subverted: Theme and Variations in the Four "Royal Court" Plays of John Arden, 1957-1960, 1972; Copelin, David (Box 22)
  - African Theatre: A Nigerian Prototype, 1972; Ezeokoli, Victoria Chinwenma (Box 22)
  - Theatre of Fact: A Study of Plays Dramatizing Contemporaneous Events, 1973; Beacham, Richard C.; 2 copies (Box 23)
  - Theatre of Friendship, Theatre of Intelligence: Three Studies of Self and Other in Modern Drama: Henrik Ibsen, Albert Camus, Harold Pinter, 1973; Frutkin, Reynold F. (Box 23)
  - The Raid on the Boulevard: French Playwriting During the Nineteen-Twenties, 1973; Ostergren, Christopher (Box 24)
  - Parody and Counter-Mimesis in Western Drama, 1973; Schechter, Joel (Box 24)
  - The New Woman in the Drama of Büchner, Ibsen, Strindberg, and Brecht, 1974; Mackay, Barbara (Box 24)
  - The Ethical Role of Women in Six Euripidean Tragedies, 1974; Trousdell, Richard (Box 25)
  - The Actor Behind the Mask: A Study in the Dramatist's Manipulation of the Actor's Relationship to his Role as Perceived by the Audience, 1976; Kalish, Eugene; 2 copies (Box 25)
  - Franz Xaver Kroetz: The Volksstück in Transition, 1977; Klaic, Dragan Milenko; 2 (Box 26)
  - Melodrama and Realism, 1978; Hauptman, Ira Jay; 2 (Box 26)
  - Images of Women in Restoration Comedy, 1978; Larson, Judith Rae; 2 (Box 27)
  - Love and Loneliness in Isolation: The Theatrical World of Athol Fugard, 1978; Vandenbroucke, Russell; 2 (Box 28)
  - All the World's a Stage: That Shakespeherian Rag, 1979; Cadden, Michael (Box 28)
  - Modern Lyric Drama: The Opera Librettos of Hugo von Hofmannsthal, Bertolt Brecht, W. H. Auden, Gertrude Stein, 1979; Marx, Robert Kirk; 2 (Box 29)
  - Shakespearean Ritual and Ceremony, 1979; Russell, Thomas Wright III; 2 (Box 30)
  - The Political Theater in Bengal, 1981; Bharucha, Rustom (Box 31)
  - Daimonic Drama, 1981; Fischer, Eileen (Box 31)
  - The Scene of the Crime: Legal Representations and the Grammar of the Dramatic Text, 1983; King, W. D. (Box 31)
  - Making a Script: Preamble To An Archive of West Indian Drama, 1984; Clarke, Betty E.; 2 copies (Box 32)
  - Moliere: The Buffoon, the Charlatan, and the Ape, 1984; Marks, Jonathan; 2 (Box 33)
  - Selfhood and Silence: Imminent Reconciliation In Mozart's Magic Flute, 1987; Evenden, Michael; 2 copies (Box 34)
  - Prologue To Blood Wedding: A Study of the Early Plays of Federico Garcia Lorca, 1987; Giner, Oscar (Box 34)
  - Beckett in Performance, 1987; Kalb, Jonathan; 2 (Box 35)
  - Robert Wilson and His Collaborators, 1987; Shyer, Laurence Douglas (Box 35)
  - "All Life Transfigured": Structural and Thematic Disillusionment in Shaw's Heartbreak House, 1988; Henderson, Heather Donielson; 2 (Box 36)
  - Three Great German Comedies: A Critical Anthology, 1989; Cardullo, Bert (Box 37)
  - The Crommelynck Mystery: New Perspectives on the Dramatic Work of Fernand Crommelynck, vol. I, 1989; Piette, Alain (Box 37)
  - The Crommelynck Mystery: New Perspectives on the Dramatic Work of Fernand Crommelynck, vol. II-V, 1989; Piette, Alain (Box 38)
  - Theologies of Liberation: The Historical Interconnections of Religion, Politics, and Theater in Latin America, 1990; Versenyi, Adam (Box 39)
  - A Passion for Perfection: Shaw as Job, 1991; Brody, Jean (Box 39)
  - The Shadow Poetics, 1991; Clubb, Merrel Dare, IV (Box 39)
  - The Fifth Province: Seeking the Spiritual in Modern Irish Drama, 1991; Robbins, Joan E. (Box 40)
  - Gender and Politics in Greek Tragedy, 1991; Zelenak, Michael X. (Box 40)
  - From Court to Boulevard: Three French Comedies, 1992; Magruder, James Richard (Box 40)
  - Tradition and Transformation: The Making of the British History Play after 1956, 1993; Borreca, Art (Box 41)
  - Soviet Dramatic Satire in the Twenties: A Critical Anthology of Three Plays by Bulgakov, Erdman and Mayakovsky, 1993; Coleman, C. B. (Box 41)
  - Buzz Goodbody and Her Hamlet: A Study, 1994; Wolff-Wilkinson, Lila (Box 42)
  - The Queer as Drama Critic, 1994; McNulty, Charles (Box 42)
  - Gorgons and other Goddesses: Transgression and Transformation in Euripidean Drama, 1995; Wilde, Lisa Ann; 2 (Box 42)
  - Thomas Bernhard: Surfaces and Silences, 1996; Jiu, Jenn-Jung (Box 43)
  - Production Casebook for Ibsen's Lady from the Sea, 1996; Puga, Ana (Box 40)
  - At the Nexus of Dance and Drama: The Theater of Martha Graham, 1997; Lordi, Karen E. (Box 43)
  - Toward a Dramaturgy of the "Other": English-Language Playwriting in Asia and the Creation of a Global Theatre Perspective, 1997; Ray, Timothy J. (Box 43)
  - Three French Playwrights For the New Millennium, 1997; Schneider, Robert (Box 43)
  - The Essential Experience in Shakespeare's Comedies: The New Hermeneutic Synthesis, 1998; Borg, Dominica M. (Box 43)
  - Circles of Meaning: A Cultural Approach to West Sumatran Theatre, 1998; Latrell, Craig Thomas (Box 51)
  - If You Care to Blast For It: Excavating the Lost Comic Masterpieces of the American Canon, 1999; Sheehy, Catherine (Box 44)
  - Shakespeare's Twelfth Night: An American Sign Language Translation, 2001; Novak, Peter Joseph (Box 45)
  - Hofmannsthal and Kokoschka: Theaters of Brutality, 2001; Swanson, Christopher (Box 45)
  - Four Plays by Chekhov: New Translations of The Seagull, Uncle Vanya, Three Sisters, and The Cherry Orchard, accompanied by a critical introduction in three parts, 2002; Johnsen-Neshati, Kristin; 2 (Box 46)
  - All the Universe a Stage: Three Plays of Calderon de la Barca, 2003; Davis, Rick (Box 46)
  - The Theatre of Juan Mayorga, 2005; Padilla, María E. (Box 47)
  - The American Showstopper: Nationalism and Musical Theater, 1942-2004, vol. I-II, 2005; Rugg, Rebecca Ann (Box 47)
  - The End of the Absurd: Protest and Performance of May '68, 2006; Bredeson, Kate (Box 47)
  - Suzan-Lori Parks' History Plays, 2006; Garrett, Shawn-Marie (Box 48)
  - Landscape Consciousness on the Modern Stage: Ibsen, Chekhov, Strindberg, 2006; Holzapfel, Amy Strahler (Box 48)
  - The American Negro Theatre: Staging Inter-Racialism in Harlem, 1940-49, 2006; Shandell, Jonathan (Box 48)
  - Astor Place in 1849: The Dramaturgy of a Riot, 2007; Brizzell-Bates, Cynthia Taylor; 2 (Box 49)
  - Developing American Drama: Representative Productions of the Theatre Guild, 2007; Case, Claudia Wilsch (Box 49)
  - Four Neo-Classical French Plays: Comedies and Tragedies by Corneille and Racine, 2008; Carver, Gordon (Box 49)
  - Playing the Whore: The Prostitute as Avatar in Modern Drama, 1853-1953, 2008; Rusch, Rachael (Box 50)
  - More Lost Than Found: Charting Ralph Lemon's Geography Trilogy From Conception Through Performance, 2009; Profeta, Katherine (Box 50)
  - The politics of primitivism in German expressionist drama 1907-1920., 2013; Achen, Monica (Box 51)
  - Last stop, Germania: history and nation in the post-1989 German theater., 2013; Cornish, Matthew Richard (Box 51)
  - Viral performance: theatrical circulations in a new media age., 2013; Felton-Dansky, Miriam (Box 52)
  - Naked theater: a translation of three Spanish modernist plays., 2013; Rodriguez, Jorge J. (Box 52)
  - (Up)Staging themselves: four translations of German romantic self-reflexive plays with a critical introduction., 2013; Shaw, Jennifer Louise Jude (Box 52)